[Music]
hello and welcome to the ask a budget
show how are you all doing i hope you're
doing great
uh today we discuss uh history
geopolitics current affairs and so on so
uh let me take a look at who all is
there
right now with us
i can see rohit priyanshi devosman swita
monuni
and lots of other people
great to have you all with us tonight
or today wherever you are depending on
where you are
and with that said let us get into the
questions as always we have a whole lot
of questions to cover
so shall we get into it let's take
question number one
question number one is by tejas what's
your take on the lion controversy on the
ashok
so what's this controversy the lion
controversy let's take a look at what
the controversy is all about
um um let me uh
where's the image
yes this is the image take a look
so this apparently is the controversial
image
the uh new parliament building is being
constructed and the lion emblem of the
indian nation has been placed on top
and mr modi the prime minister posed
with it
and apparently this is controversial
so uh
those who are upset some people are
upset about this they're saying that the
lions look too scary
why are the lions mouths open
why are they bearing their fangs why
can't they be more civilized and keep
their mouths mouths closed and not scare
the hell out of everybody
so the controversy is about the lions
having open mouths and bearing their
fangs apparently it looks extremely
scary
and that's what's upsetting some people
yeah so that's real that that is the
controversy so it's okay if other
nations have scary emblems
uh england for instance has three lions
on its emblem even though there are no
lions in england that's fine they can do
it
wales has a dragon apparently
dragons don't even exist but but that's
fine the chinese their national emblem
is more or less a dragon which is a
mythical imaginary creature scary
creature that's fine they can have it
but the indian
nation must have a non-scary emblem
emblem
a non-scary symbol
this is very aggressive very uh it
evokes violence
and aggression we are a nation of
non-violence and hindsight and all that
nonsense
so that is apparently the controversy
right that is what people some certain
sections of the political class and
society apparently are upset about so
here's what they would like the indian
national emblem to be like
this is what they wanted to be
hello kitty
yeah
you you uh keep this as the indian
national emblem on the
on top of the parliament and everywhere
else that is what will appease them they
want india to be reduced to this
well
tough luck because it's not going to
happen
so that is what the controversy is about
and
just disregard this nonsense india is
what it is and if people find it scary
so be it
it's time for a change after a thousand
years for india to be a little bit
scarier than what it's been like
time to
dump
non-violence and all that nonsense into
the
into the trash bin
yeah because that's how it is so that's
my take on this very brief right next
vishnu says i um why don't you take my
questions i tried for months and you
never asked answered my question please
take it this time all right sir i found
it so let's take it
there are four questions so because it's
been several months he's asking for the
same thing all right let's take four
question number one is we know that the
maratha defeated the mughals then why
didn't they recover the temples and
hindu monuments destroyed by the mughals
well i i don't know
uh i am not a real expert in maratha
history
i don't know why this was not done the
marathas did recover the whole of india
from the mughals they did
free liberate india from foreign
oppression
they reunified india all the way to up
to parts of southern afghanistan and
much of the indian subcontinent was
under maratha rule so i don't know
why they did not do what what you're
saying and they also allowed the
so-called
nominal
mughal emperor to stay in power in delhi
he was essentially the mayor of delhi
nothing more but he was called the
mughal emperor of the whole of india
they allowed this individual this turk
to stay in power in the city of delhi
even though he had no real power it was
just a nominal figurehead and they
allowed him to stay so i don't know why
this was done maybe there were political
reasons for this yeah i don't know but
yes that's a question that i would like
some
historians or experts in maratha history
to answer
maybe that maybe they're in power for
not long enough maybe the the empire
crumbled very rapidly within a century
or so maybe there was too much
politicking within the maratha empire
yeah the peshwas and all that came and
went some of them were really great
people no doubt about it some of the
vegetables were really great chaturapa
shivaji was one of the greatest of
course but later on there was a lot of
infighting among the marathas and that
eventually led to the decline in the the
defeat
of the maratha empire at the hands of
the british during the during the
anglo-maratha wars
so maybe there wasn't enough time to uh
to change things in the nation they were
too busy
fighting amongst themselves for power
maybe that's the cause so i don't really
have the exact answer for that but that
seems to be the reason there was no
there was not enough time to change all
the destruction
that had been brought upon the country
by the talks over several centuries yeah
okay number two today in the army they
do salute to show respect to seniors
what gesture was used by by our ancient
army so yes today in the armed forces we
salute this way or that way whichever it
is if you want to disrespect your
officers you salute with the left hand
that's what the indians did in 1946
during the great uh indian
naval rebellion against the british yeah
they took to saluting the british
officers with the left hand anyway so uh
today we we are copying the british
blindly salute that way what gesture was
used by our ancient army i don't know
none of us know we don't know is there
any record in our
whatever text survive from the olden
times about how
uh
about whether there was a gesture or
something like that
something similar to a salute we don't
know we don't know we have lost uh
records of that time so
yeah it's a good question but we don't
have the answer to that
okay number three the organization of
party or netaji bose
is it still in india or is it dissolved
okay let's uh
let's take a look here
um
where is google search
let's go to google search
um
[Music]
let's uh so the organization of netaji
bose was called the forward block
forward block
so this
organization
the all india forward block
is a left-wing nationalist political
party in india
it emerged as a faction within the
indian national congress in 1939 led by
subhash chandra bose so clearly it still
exists
the party re-established as an
independent political party after the
independence of india it has its main
stronghold in west bengal and so on and
so forth so the all india forward block
was
founded
by subhash chandra bose in 1939 and it
still exists
so that is your answer my dear sir
that's your answer all right let us go
back to the questions
number four why did the english people
name their company
the east india company
why not india company or whatever well
it's yeah that's a good question
so as i suppose you all know that
individual christoforo colombo
christopher columbus
set out westwards from spain across the
atlantic ocean in the hope of
discovering or rediscovering india
yeah
he shut out with i don't know two or
three ships three three four whatever
the number is look it up so he set out
on his voyage in order to rediscover
india and claim it for the spanish crown
for his masters and mr for his master
and mistress the king and queen of spain
and he
ended up blundering all the way
westwards and discovering
the the continent of the of the of north
america
he first discovered some islands in the
caribbean and hispaniola which is
present-day haiti etc and so on but yeah
he is credited with the discovery of
america even though long before him it
was the vikings
life eriksen
etc who discovered america anyway
so when christopher columbus came up on
upon this great land mass he said we
have discovered india this is the india
this is india and he called the natives
of this region the the native americans
the the caribs the arawak etc he called
them indians and he went back to spain
and said i have discovered india there's
a lot of gold blah blah blah lies all
lies he knew i suppose he would have
known it's not quite like the way india
was described in uh
older european texts because india had
extensive contacts with europe
so
christopher columbus said i have
discovered india and that's why the
people of the native americans are still
kind of still called indians native
indians red indians whatever right
pejoratively
so that was the west indies the west
they called it the western part of india
for whatever reason because
that was the to the west of europe
even today the cricket team that that
region is still called the west indies
even though it's not india indies means
the the parts of various parts of india
the indies so it's called the west
indies
which is completely incorrect it's just
the caribbean region or whatever you
want to call it but it's still called
the west indies
so that's what the europeans discovered
first
uh why did they have to look for india
because the turks had cut off the land
road to india
uh the land route passed through
anatolia present-day turkey the which
was
a
part of the byzantine empire the eastern
roman empire for a very long time the
turks conquered this region and
therefore the europeans were no longer
able to go eastwards via land in order
to reach india for whatever they needed
from india or the trade activities and
all that so that's why it was a great
quest for them to rediscover india a
different sea route maybe towards india
so
christopher columbus said what though
that land i've discovered in the west is
india
eventually the europeans uh realized
this was
a complete mystic it's a new landmass
that he has discovered but they still
kept on calling it the west indies
right
and therefore when they when india was
eventually
when vasco de gama eventually
rediscovered india going around the cape
of good hope
from south of africa
that part of india the europeans started
calling it east india
even today some people call india east
india for whatever reason
and that's why the the english when they
they founded their company at the at the
end of the 17th century
which century 17 most likely
yeah something 16th century at the end
of the 16th century
yeah so they called it the east india
company for that reason because they now
distinguish between the west indies and
the east indies and even indonesia and
the the islands the archipelago of that
region is called the east indies even
today yeah
so it's just what the
europeans
called it
and then and so that's how they
distinguish the two geographical regions
and that is in short why the english
called their company the east india
company
full ranidas says
take this question with my third attempt
all right
is or
are there any nations that never got
invaded by another country
and which never invaded another country
in their history if there are then what
are they
is there any nation
that has never been invaded
uh some some people were saying in
response to this question that japan has
never been invaded while fyi japan is
under us occupation
since 1945 japan has been invaded
successfully and conquered and
subjugated and colonized
by the u.s it is currently under u.s
occupation yeah so japan is not the case
and even if you go back in japanese
history to the 12th 13th whatever
century
13th 14th century you had the mongol
invasion of japan which was not entirely
successful the kamikaze divine divine
wind happened and that's why the mongols
were unable to
uh
complete their conquest of uh japan but
they did land on the island of sushima
et cetera and so on so japan is not the
case
some people say switzerland well sudan
has been invaded multiple times
conquered by the romans by julius caesar
who conducted
a full uh
genocide of the of the helvetian tribes
the the celtic tribes in the in the
region in switzerland and again the
habsburg empire
invaded and conquered parts of sudan or
maybe the whole of it william tell is
that great
great rebel who fought against them and
so on even the french
uh
conquered
switzerland so switzerland is not the
case i don't think there is any nation
or any geographical part of the world
which has never been invaded and never
conquered
you go back far enough in history every
part of the world has
suffered invasions and
for some time at least conquests by uh
other powers
is there any country that never invaded
another country
well
none that i know of people have been for
for the longest time on social media
people were claiming that india is a
peaceful pacifistic country we haven't
invaded anybody ever well that's a
complete lie obviously
india has
invaded
other
geographical regions multiple times as
we know i hope
you know
so i can't think of any nation that has
never been invaded and which has never
invaded anybody yeah
maybe the swiss never tried invading
anybody if you look at the nation state
of switzerland
maybe maybe that could be the case
perhaps so yeah that's just how it is if
you look go back long enough in history
you will find all kinds of such things
happening the nation state system is a
very new system it goes back to the uh
um the treaty of westphalia which is
quite recent
relatively speaking and so on yeah so
that's the answer
okay miguel diaz says you never miss a
chance
to portray emperor ashok equivalent to
somebody like aurangzeb ashok never
fought a single war after kalinga and
was crucial in spreading influence of
buddhism throughout the subcontinent it
is also said he gave he didn't give up
or give up on be being the devotee of
lord shiva even after
adopting buddhism
so one cannot hate him on the basis of
not being a hindu
no
what makes you say i hate ashok i admire
the guy he was somebody worth of worthy
of admiration
think about it you want to compare ashok
and orang zip all right let's do it
ashok
um
yeah well he came to power he became the
emperor of india at the expense of his
siblings it is said apparently that he
had a hundred of his
siblings brothers or half brothers etc
killed in order to become emperor
which obviously could be an exaggeration
maybe he had 10 20 of them killed in
those days emperor's youtube used to
have multiple wives his father
bindu sir
may have had multiple wives and may have
had lots of children it's possible yeah
so we know that there was and we know
that ashok was not the uh
the uh crown prince somebody one of his
brothers was the crown prince and he
took over power he you took over power
at the expense of his brother and
everybody else yeah sure he did that uh
very machiavellian right
and then uh
he
started following the pizza precepts of
about the dharma which was at that time
a reasonably obscure sect of dharma
and it is known that he was a very cruel
person he had lots of people tortured
imprisoned beheaded killed etc he
apparently enjoyed cruelty
chand ashok he was called he had
something called ashok's hell which is a
prison in which people were tortured and
apparently he had he ordered the killing
of eighteen thousand aji weekers yeah
right people who belonged who belong to
that particular sect or philosophical
school of thought of hinduism and so on
yeah he was cruel okay we get it but
what is also true is that he unified the
entire indian subcontinent he
he made
he he
made the entire region extremely
prosperous there was a rule of law
there was discipline there was rule of
law uh he indulged he engaged in
diplomacy with far away nations he spoke
about various things that he was in
contact with ptolemy of egypt certain
kings in uh in the west in parts of
europe in
the middle east etc he sent embassies to
all these kings he spread dharma far and
wide he said that the regions as far as
greece and west of greece had been
conquered by dharma right that's what he
said he also had
contacts with he sent embassies to
swarna swarnabhumi which obviously
refers to thailand
to sri lanka he sent his own
children
uh sangamitra and what's his name
mahindra to sri lanka established good
relations there spread dharma and so on
so
he may have been
a cruel king to those who were
who posed a threat to him he may have
enjoyed
a certain sadistic tendencies but
overall
he improved
the quality of life and the prosperity
of his people
vishnu gupta said that the highest
morality for a king is that his nation
and its people should prosper he's
ashoka certainly ensured that
he built far more than he destroyed
he spread dharma far and wide he built
so many schools viharas monasteries
temples what
not right yeah sure he
of course we cannot condone what he did
in kalinga
uh the conquest of kalinga lots of more
than a hundred thousand soldiers died in
the battle and i don't know what else he
did over there so yeah that is a dark
chapter in history but if you look at it
from a larger perspective overall
the entire
subcontinent prospered significantly
under ashok
right
and he did stamp out all descent with an
iron fist
i think
his grandfather's mentor would have been
very proud of him my boy good job
his grandfather's mentor his grandfather
was chandragupta maury obviously and his
grandfather's mentor was vaishnava
ashoka lived his life on chanakyan
principles
as per chanakyan principles
we don't know if ashok and chanakya were
con
knew each other uh we'll have to look at
the dates when they are supposed to have
lived but it's possible that as a child
he may have known his grandfather's
mentor possibly and anyway vishnu
influence still exists today so
obviously ashok would have followed that
so i think overall ashok was an
extremely great man a great emperor of
india sure some he was not lord ram he
was not as benevolent and kind as lord
ram and he was certainly not as kind and
nice as the the various gupta emperors
and so on so forth yeah sure
but he was overall great for india
so certain character flaws may exist
that's okay
and i would say
that today's politicians can learn a
thing or two
today's leaders of india could possibly
learn a thing or two from a shock i'm
not saying this or that overall
holistically all right don't get me
wrong
so i think he is
ashok is a man who's that is worthy of
admiration
from a realistic pragmatic perspective
from a chanakyan perspective
hating ashok no
i don't hate ashok by any means
whatsoever
i
let me repeat let me reiterate ashok is
worthy of admiration he overcomes so
many obstacles
he over
he overcame the greatest of odds and
succeeded
and took his entire civilization forward
he is worthy of admiration now what
about this individual called aurangzeb
aurangzeb was a barbarian
aurangzeb did the exact opposite of
ashok
ashok made his country his nation his
civilization prosperous and its people
prosperous overall holistically
he did his utmost to spread his nation's
culture worldwide he turned
dharma into a global force
that is what ashok did what did
aurangzeb did to do
he tried to stamp out the native culture
and civilization in the of the land that
he ruled
he may have been born in india he he
acted like a foreign barbarian
he tried to bring in a foreign culture
into india and and impose it by force by
destroying everything that was of any
value
in the in the land he ruled
and obviously
we cannot condone we cannot disregard
the fact that he indulged in outright
genocide in india
and some some people would say oh what's
the proof what's the evidence blah blah
blah well you don't trust me okay some
people say i'm uh i'm this or that or
whatever i cannot be trusted well
i suppose you would trust your masters
in the us
i suppose you would trust the new york
times
here's what the new york times has to
say
population control marauder style okay
you can look this up online this is a
new york times infographic
right
it's about the various genocidal
barbarians who have ruled various parts
of the world
and uh our dear old aurangzeb figures
very much in this where does it figure
let me enlarge this take a look
orang zeb according to the new york
times figures in data aurangzeb was
responsible for the deaths of 4.6
million indians all right 4.6 million
indians is a genocide
and
remember this is the new york times
which is very much anti-india so these
figures are
are obviously extremely conservative
figures
to reach the real figures of how many
people orgasm would have killed you to
multiply this by at least 10.
so that would bring him on in the same
category as mao zedong
so that yeah that's that's the kind of
uh
place that aurangzeb occupies most
likely he killed way more indians than
that
all right
so there is no
basis for comparing ashok and aurangzeb
one was a saint the other was a devil
ashok was a saint compared to aurangzeb
so that's what i have to say to you my
dear friend miguel diaz
that's all i have to say to you
right
sikha bhattacharya says how was the end
of the indus valley civilization and
beginning of the aryan civilization and
was the beginning of aryan civilization
good for india
i am irish i study in the eighth
standard you changed my way of thinking
made me understand geopolitics which i
had never heard of before thank you
it's great to hear from you uh arish and
i'm glad that in this early age you're
interested in geopolitics history etc
great to know that
keep it up all right
so uh
what was the end of the okay indus
valley civilization aryan civilization
etc see these are foreign concepts the
indus valley civilization which starts
and ends then aryan invasion starts and
that is the result of that is the uh
that's what gives rise to india as it is
today that is
what the way they teach history the
truth is this
there is unbroken cultural continuity in
india going back at least 10 000 years
and there is undeniable archaeological
evidence lots of archaeological evidence
that demonstrates that the sa the
culture that exists in india today
its predecessor culture
existed even 10 000 years ago so the
culture is unbroken you can see certain
elements of culture throughout
you find statuettes of ladies from the
so-called
saraswati sindhu phase the so-called
harappan or indus valley phase
in which those little statues of ladies
have a vermillion sindhur in their in
their on their forehead right the same
way indian ladies still wear today
you find shiva linga's thresholds in the
so called indus valley or harappan phase
of india civilization
you find so many other examples of the
indian culture that still exist today in
the so-called harappan era the uh
archaeologist john marshall the who was
the head of the asi in the 1920s 1930s
somewhere that like that he said that
the indus valley culture is so dis is so
remarkably i mean i'm paraphrasing
paraphrasing
he said it is so remarkably indian that
is it is virtually indistinguishable
from present-day hinduism that's what
this english man said more than a
century about a century ago right so
the culture and the civilization is the
same
there is no such thing as aryan
civilization or industrial civilization
there is only one thing called indian
civilization which is an unbroken
cultural continuum 10 000 plus years
right so uh you can say there are phases
in india civilization there was a
so-called some people call it a
pre-harappan phase whatever that is then
there is the harappan phase
then there are other phases later on
phases pre and somewhere in there we
have the vedic phase so according to
our history textbooks which are taught
in school uh the
indus valley phase was
brought to an end
it was made to collapse by a foreign
invasion by an invasion from abroad by
the so-called aryan people there is a
lie there is no such thing there is no
evidence not a single scrap of evidence
for that
show me a single archaeological piece of
evidence for an invasion or migration or
tourism or picnic and i will change my
mind
there is no such thing
right so
aryan civilization i mean the word arya
in sanskrit means noble or civilized
right so it's not something that came
from abroad from outside it is something
that emerged out of india india was
called arya and later on indians
migrated westwards to various parts of
the world westwards one of these
migrations was to persia the parshwa
clan of the vedic people migrated
westward settled down in what is now
called persia after their name
parshua became persia
and they started using arya as an ethnic
self-designation
but arya originally means
noble or civilized so if any people are
to be called aryans it is the indians
and the iranians also yeah that's it so
there was no aryan civilization it's
just indian civilization and the indus
valley uh what they call the indus
valley civilization is a certain time
phase time period of the 10 000 plus
year history of indian civilization so
the point to be understood is that
indian civilization
did not start four thousand years ago or
five thousand years ago whatever it is
it has existed for more than ten
thousand years we have discovered
archaeologists and marine marine
archaeologists have discovered a sunken
city in the gulf of khambhat
of the of the coast of gujarat which
dates back at least 12 000 years
at least 12 000 years and that looks
exactly it is it is planned and designed
just like the so-called harappan cities
so that tells you that the indian
civilization goes back even beyond ten
thousand years maybe beyond twelve
thousand years i mean if you if if they
had the ability if our ancestors had the
ability to construct a large
massive well-planned city twelve
thousand years before today that ability
would have developed over several
thousand years
right the the engineering knowledge etc
would have developed it would not have
appeared overnight
that also takes time years centuries
thousands of years to develop so indian
civilization is the oldest known
civilization in the entire
known
world
yes
there was no aryan invasion that is an
entire fabrication and today even the
geneticists who have been who have been
pushing that for for years are now
coming around to claim to now amending
their story to say that the so-called
step ancestry that also has
an eastern
origin whatever that eastern means and
so on
so uh i hope that answers your question
uh keep it up keep studying keep
learning and all the best sikha
all right saurabh says how is the dating
of the rig veda using sarkar al's study
is there any possibility that the rig
without being older of the rig weather
being older than 6000 bc as the
saraswati was it in its peak around 7
000 8 000 bc or even before that what
are your thoughts on this okay so i've
written about this in the past so let me
show you what that is what is this a
study by sarkar et al
let's go there
let me show you the actual research
paper
where is it
this is the research paper it's uh it's
in nature it's from 2016. it says the
title is oxygen isotope in
archaeological bioappetites from india
implications to climate change and
decline of the bronze age harappan
civilization and so on yeah so let's
take a look at the abstract which is the
summary
the antiquity and decline of the bronze
age harappan civilization in the indus
river valleys is an enigma in
archaeology weakening of the monsoon
after 5000 bp and droughts throughout
asia is a strong contender for the
harappan collapse although controversy
exists about the synchronicity of
climate change in the collapse of
civilization one reason for this
controversy is a lack of continuous
record of cultural levels and paleo
monsoon change in close proximity we
report a high resolution oxygen isotope
record of animal teeth bone phosphates
from an archaeological trench itself at
birana northwestern india
preserving all cultural levels of the
civilization miranda was part of a high
concentration of settlements along the
dried up
mythical
vedic river valley saraswati and
extension of the
river in the desert
isotope and archaeological data suggest
that the pre-harappan started inhabiting
this area along the mighty gagar river
fed by intensified monsoon from 9000 to
7000 kilo years thousand years before
present the monsoon monotonically
declined after seven thousand thousand
seven thousand years yet the settlements
continued to survive from early to
mature harappan time
our study suggests other that other
causes like change in subsistence
subsistence strategy by shifting crop
patterns other than climate change was
responsible for harappan collapse
so that is what it says and there's the
whole details so you can look up the
paper it is available online it is not
behind a pay wall
you can look it up
so that is the paper that is what it
says now how do we use this
to uh to date the rig away them right
that's the question so this paper says
that the indian monsoon started
declining monotonically around five
earlier dosing seven thousand bc seven
thousand years before present whatever
five six seven thousand years before
present maybe eight thousand
around that time the monsoon was very
heavy very heavy in india then it
started declining monotonically means it
was a very slow very gradual decline
very slow very very gradual it took
thousands of years
for it to become so intense that the
decline of the monsoon that the great
river saraswati started drying out
so they clearly identified the
river with the
still call it mythical today they don't
call it mythical anymore in newer papers
it's now established that the great
river that is spoken of in ancient
indian vedic literature is the same as
the enormous massive dry riverbed that
we find in this region which is
a continuation of what is now called the
the gagar hakka river which is now a
seasonal river which dries out uh when
it is not raining
so that is now clearly identified there
is no doubt about it
that it is the saraswati river the
sarasota river of ancient indian history
so
how do we date the rigveda based on this
so they have found that this great river
the mother of indian civilization
started
drying out slowly with
contempt
as a consequence of the monotonical
decline of the indian monsoon which
starts around 7 000 or so years before
today
right
so as the monsoon declines as the
intensity of the monsoon declines this
river which is a
monsoon fed rain-fed river also
naturally starts declining and
eventually it dries out about
about
3 500 years before today in large parts
it would have eventually uh called
ended as a big lake then which dried out
which is now the thar desert the
rajasthan desert
so
now in the rig veda the river saraswati
is mentioned extensively
there are lots and lots of mentions of
the great river saraswati and how is
this river described how is the great
river saraswati described in the rigveda
it is called the greatest of rivers it
is called a glorious river it is
described as a loudly roaring river it
is described as the mother of floods
all right
so what does it sound like does it sound
like a river in decline
or does it sound like a majestic mighty
river in its prime
clearly
the rig veda is describing a river that
is in its prime it is not describing a
river that is in decline
so when did the decline start
around 7000 bc
so
or maybe 6000 bc whatever you want to
call it uh about six or seven thousand
years before today that is for sure
so what does that lead us to conclude
logic
one plus one equals two
it tells you that the rig weather has to
be would have been written around the
time when the river was in its prime
not when the river had already started
declining
which means that is at least six seven
thousand years old based on this rough
approximation there is no other way of
interpreting the data
the rigveda is not describing some
mythological imaginary river it's
describing a very real physical river
loudly roaring river the mother of
floods and there's only one dry riverbed
in this region which is loud enough to
fit the description but that is large
enough to fit this description which is
the well it is which is now
definitively identified as the extinct
river saraswati
so that is
the logic behind this which tells us
that the rig weather would have been
written at least 6000 years before today
around that time so that totally
completely annihilates and falsifies the
rn invasion or migration or tourism or
picnic myth
which says that the aryans
arrived in india about 1500 bc
around 1500 bc the river was mostly dry
in the southern southern regions near
the sea
it simply cannot describe
that dried out river
so and and
this this uh narrative says that the
aryans who arrived in india settled down
in the sapta sindhu region in western
india and then wrote the rigveda and the
vedic literature well if they arrived at
the time they would have found a
dried-out region
yeah so this completely destroys this
false narrative completely totally
so we can roughly date the rig with our
at around 6000 or 7000 years before
today maybe older but at least that old
right
next question
tushit says will the britishers ever
accept a brown prime minister like rishi
sunak or prithi patel the british my
dear friend will accept anybody their
masters tell them to accept
who owns the uk who actually controls
and runs the uk it's the americans
the uk
is a vasal state
of the us
the u.s completely owns essentially the
uk so the british will do whatever the
americans tell them to do yeah there
will be a democratic process for show
and all that and somebody will be
appointed as the prime minister
within the party there will be this
inter-party intra-party struggle and
there are three four candidates who are
still standing and one of them will be
appointed uh i'm not sure if pretty
patel is still in the fray rishi sonak
seems to be the front uh the
the main contender right now
so if the the overlord overlords deemed
that rishi izunak will do a good job as
our servant then he will be
appointed as a prime minister and the
people of britain will quietly accept it
they will have been accepting whatever
has been done to them over the past 30
essentially since that guy tony blair
became the prime minister
he is described as a u.s poodle
which is a rather unkind thing to say
but some people have described him
described him that way so ever since
tony blair came to power the entire u.s
uk dynamic changed
uh
and uh yeah
so so that's when the uk became a
complete
wasall state of the us and that's when
strangely enough the irish insurgency
ended strangely enough isn't that
strange anyhow
okay two questions
rahul says since boris johnson will be
replaced as uk pm and roshi rishi sunak
and penny modont are considered the
prime candidates who among these is more
pro india who should be the next pm that
so that india benefits the most
harshit says
uh thank you rashid
i was having this question for a long
time after boris johnson resigned as pm
there's speculation about who will be
the next pm
what type of uk pm do you think
perfectly suits fits or interest
a good uk pm who looks india is a
trustworthy reliable friend can help
each other diplomatically or aggressive
nt india pm
get out of the colonial commonwealth
other things um
and what else
we can't afford to do when we were pro
india ukb okay
see
uk prime ministers their actual stated
job description
is to
serve the uk's national interest
now the uk is a colony of the u.s
therefore all
uk prime ministers who last any
reasonable amount of time have their
are aligned
with u.s geopolitical interests
and the us doesn't see india
as a nation that should be allowed to
rise too much
they have already made a massive mistake
with the child with china they will not
make that mistake again with india
and therefore any prime minister who
comes to power in the uk and lasts for a
long time will be able to last only
because they are aligned with the
american geopolitical interests and and
are a good servant to the us
that's just how the way the way it is
and therefore no matter who comes to
power it's not it's not going to be the
case that that person will be very pro
india or even moderately pro india
the uk is not an important nation today
it is not some massive major
geopolitical power the uk is not even a
second great power the uk is is a colony
it's a vasal state of the u.s just like
japan is today
japan is even worse far further down
down the road japan is under permanent
u.s occupation well there is a certain
element of u.s occupation in the uk as
well
all the uk's
uh nuclear missiles
are essentially american nuclear
missiles and i don't think the the uk
prime minister has the launch calls for
the codes for those missions yes those
missiles are placed in
british submarines but i don't think the
uk prime minister has the authority to
launch the missiles even if he or she
wants to
so that is how far it has gone those
missiles are american missiles
the uk had its own space program which
was ended dismantled yeah they had good
rockets
they had hydrogen peroxide fueled
rockets if i remember
they were dismantled
for whatever reason so that's how it is
so whoever comes to power in the uk
is not going to be
in any way pro india even if rishi so
not comes to power obviously he's a guy
who has indian origin it makes no
difference he's going to serve his
masters he's going to serve the uk in
the u.s he is not going to be pro india
in any way whatsoever neither is priti
patel gonna be
pro india
if at all they will be under more
pressure to demonstrate that they are
loyal to the to the empire not to india
so they may end up being even more
anti-india than
re than other prime ministers have been
just to demonstrate that we are not
uh you know
we are loyal to the master so that's how
it is that's how i say it it makes no
difference to india who comes to power
in the uk the uk doesn't matter the uk
is not an important geopolitical force
the uk is a subsidiary it's an
it's a it's a colony essentially of the
us and the real power is in the u.s the
uk doesn't matter it's not even a
second-rate geopolitical power it's a
third-rate geopolitical power that's all
it is i am so i apologize if i've
offended everybody but that is a fact
okay shiva says if the u.s is the
superpower in the current ruling empire
how come the pound currency is the
strongest in the world and not the usd
and could you tell
a bit more about the finance
geopolitical situation the collapsing
dollar hegemony please okay let's take
the first part of the question if the us
is the superpower and the current ruling
empire how come the pound is the
strongest in the currency in the world
not the usd
this strength of a currency is not
determined by exchange rates
it's not determined by exchange rates
there are certain currencies that have
an even stronger exchange rate than the
pound compared to the us dollar it means
nothing
the strength of a currency
it is determined by how widely that
currency is in use
and whether the currency is the global
reserve currency or not
the only
currency that can be called the global
reserve currency reserve currency today
is the u.s dollar
and this happened in 1944 45 when the uh
as a consequence of the bretton woods
agreement the bretton woods conference
and the agreement that came out of it
which officially made the us dollar the
reserve currency the global reserve
currency
it was at the time
linked to the price of gold which was
then removed
which was then removed by president
nixon
and the u.s dollar then became linked
with the price of petroleum it's now
called the petrodollar right
so um all oil transactions for the
longest time were only done in u.s
dollars and it's it's a globally
accepted currency you go to any nation
in the world you you give them u.s
dollars they will take it
yeah
the uk pound may not be that well
accepted the way the u.s dollar is so
that is why
the u.s dollar is the global reserve
currency and that
the exchange rate means nothing actually
you can have a nation with which which
has a currency that is equal to 10 u.s
dollars it doesn't mean that that nation
is a superpower or that that currency is
stronger the strength of a currency is
measured is determined by the acceptance
worldwide and it is precisely because
the us dollar is the
global reserve currency
it is because of this fact that the us
is able to impose sanctions on any
nation at will which cuts that nation
off from the global uh
trade uh
infrastructure
and it it imposes enormous hardships on
that nation because essentially
sanctions means no other nation is
allowed to trade or deal with that
nation in u.s dollars and in another
currency
so and you know the global system the
swift etc is all uh denominated
essentially based on the us dollar and
so on so that is what the fact is the
exchange rate means nothing at all
coming to the next question akhil says
why dollar two rupee conversion going on
increasing day by day india is india
taking precautionary measures to control
it all right so yes we are we are
witnessing
a certain trend
in the india in the indian rupee versus
us dollar exchange
rate
the indian rupee
is declining it has reached 80 dollars
yeah or 80 rupees per dollar or it's
somewhere around that threshold what
does it mean it means it doesn't mean
that the indian rupee is declining it's
it's it's no longer valuable india is
doing very poorly is it so
well the problem with the indian media
is that they give you cherry picked data
they don't give you the large country
the big big picture
let me offer you all
the big picture shall i
let's do it
give me a send to share my screen
now you will be able to see the what's
really happening in the world take a
look at this
so this is the way currencies are
performing against the dollar
this is from december 31 2021 until
essentially right now today is july 17th
this is until july 15 2022. see what's
going on
every single currency listed here has
dropped in value against the dollar the
dollar is getting stronger since
december 31 2021 since the beginning of
this year yeah the mexican the mexican
currency has dropped about one percent
indonesian the indonesian rupiah has
dropped about five percent
the south korean von has dropped more
than 10 percent the british pound has
dropped about
12 or so percent
the uh
euro has dropped about 11 or so the
japanese yen is about 17 or 18 weaker
the turkish lira is almost 25 weaker
than the us dollar there is a global
trend of all currencies suddenly
gradually becoming weaker against the
u.s dollar where does india figure over
here india is doing very well
look here
the indian rupee has dropped about six
or seven percent since the beginning of
the year which is
compared to all the other currencies
rather doing very well do you see now do
you see the big picture
it's not that the indian currency the
indian economy is is declining
this is a trend that's happening
worldwide the us dollar is the global
reserve currency and the us is doing
something i'm not sure what it is doing
but it has been able to manufacture this
trend as you can see every single
currency of any note
in the world every single currency that
matters in the world
is declining and india is doing rather
well compared to most other currencies
does your indian media show you this
does your favorite analyst show you this
no they will not show you this
so that's what's going on the only
currency
the only currency that is done well
in these days
is the russian ruble
even though the americans have dumped
every conceivable sanction on russia
still
the russian ruble is way stronger now
today than it was at the beginning of
the ukraine invasion
because they clearly anticipated
everything the us will throw at them and
they were very well prepared and they
knew exactly what to do about this
the russians
well
they they hold
europe's energy security in their hands
uh the the europeans need russian gas in
order to power their heaters and and for
electricity etc
they depend on russia
they depend almost entirely on russia
for their energy needs and secondly the
the russians have
linked the russian ruble with the price
of gold
it's now on the gold standard
and they have demanded that anybody who
buys petroleum or or natural gas or
anything from russia must pay in russian
rubles which means now there is a demand
for rubles when something is in demand
the price rises
so the only currency that's doing well
is the russian ruble all other
currencies
have been declining since the beginning
of the year as you see here
india is doing rather well compared to
other nations india is doing better than
the indian rupee is doing much better
than the euro
than the british pound the indian rupee
is doing much better than the japanese
yen the indian rupee is doing much
better than the turkish lira and so on
and so forth
so do not allow the media to fool you
look at the bigger picture and that's
the bigger picture
says recently we heard that lithuania
has blocked the railway line from russia
to kaliningrad
and finland and sweden are joining nato
could we see something happening at the
swalky corridor
and what might be russia's future course
of action and where could
all this lead
the world scenario too
yes all right let's take a look at the
map we have to see the map at least a
few times during my episodes so let's
take a look at the map where's the map
here is the map
so we're talking about lithuania
kaliningrad
so
first of all some of you may be asking
yourselves what is khalid ingrad
so i hope you all know where russia is
you know where india is yes
go north you have russia
go westwards you have moscow you can see
moscow here
what is kaliningrad kaliningrad is a
russian enclave you see this
this here
this is kaliningrad kaliningrad is a
port city in this entire region which is
russian territory is called kaliningrad
now it is cut off from russia
it doesn't have a connection with the
russian mainland
so that's why it's called an exclave an
exclave russian exclave
so
there is a railway line or there is a
connection that russia had
through land with kalin khalid indrad
which like you say ran from lithuania
now the lithuanians have decided to stop
allowing russia access through their
territory to kalinin kaliningrad they
have blocked the russian access
uh so that's one uh
development that's happened in recent
times
uh the russians obviously have access to
belarus belarus is like
like a russian masal state or like a
russian colony essentially yes russia
may in the future in the in the near
future perhaps place nuclear missiles in
belarus which tells you how far deep
belarus is
in the russian orbit
and so uh
utkarsh is talking about the suvalke
corridor but maybe we could see some
military action in the suval key
corridor where is the walking corridor
the suvalke corridor is this region here
between
belarus and kaliningrad along the
lithuania poland border which is about
20 30 30 40 kilometers maybe that's how
long it is so
utkarsh is saying could there be some
military action in which there is a
there is some russian
advance
along this region in order to
re-establish
contact with kaliningrad through land
i think such an eventuality would be
far-fetched the russians
i don't believe they want to open up too
many
uh
conflicts at the same time they're
already in engaged in this major
conflict in ukraine they are slowly
steadily step by step
without any time pressure
taking over parts of ukraine i'm not
sure how far they would like to go but i
am sure
that they want eventually regime change
in kiev
so that's already going on
uh the americans obviously are staying
out of it they are using proxy warfare
in ukraine
now i think it would be highly un
inadvisable
for russia to open up a new war i mean
you cannot fight multiple wars at the
same time unless
you would end up losing all of them and
we can see lots of examples in history
of people of nations that have tried to
fight too many wars at the same time and
they ended up losing germany is a great
example of that during the time
during the first world war in the second
world war they bit off too far more than
they could chew so i don't think moscow
will do anything right now right now
moscow
can access
can access kalinin kaliningrad through
the baltic sea
so there is this major port here in the
north saint petersburg
they could send supply ships etc through
the baltic sea to kaliningrad and
therefore thereby resupply the city or
whatever they need to do they can do it
that way through sea and they can also
have overflights they can use uh they
can
have connection via planes by aircraft
so that's what russia will do right now
obviously this what lithuania has done
will not be forgotten
yes
i'm sure they will pay lithuania back
when the time is right i mean that
that's what they would want to do will
it happen or not we don't know
but yes that is uh obviously a hostile
action that lithuania has taken
and right now lithium lithuania probably
has calculated that we are safer with
the western bloc with nato yes and uh
they must have calculated that the us
and nato can
save them or safeguard them or protect
them
from
russia's wrath
and that may be the correct calculation
as of today but
actions have long-term consequences so
let's see how that goes
this is something that the russians will
not forget obviously when it comes to
finland and sweden joining nato that's
not big that's not a big deal the
russians will not do anything about that
finland and sweden are anyway de facto
in the western orbit in the u.s orbit in
the nato's in the nato orbit
so making it
formal is not going to change much in
the real world
it's just like putting a paper you know
a stamp on it that's it they're already
very much in the nato orbit
so making it official will not really
change anything on the ground it's
already de facto the case that they are
part of nato or in the on the same page
as nato
so i would say that there is not a very
monumental development moscow has always
known that the fin the finns have been
on the side of nato and so have been the
swedes and the norwegians and the danes
so that is where we are i don't foresee
any immediate uh
escalation of hostilities in the suwalke
corridor i don't see anything happen
happening right now the russians can
still resupply kaliningrad and they can
still contact kaliningrad
so things will go on as they are right
now but this could be possibly
something that leads to a future
conflict maybe
several years in the future that is a
possibility immediately right now i
don't foresee
any
uh
any hostilities escalating out of this
as of today as of right now
right next question
akash says in a documentary that i
recently watched an american government
official was saying that china is too
strong for india to handle in every
sector including the military it treats
arunachal pradesh as its own land of
historical significance calling it
southern tibet he connected this with a
similar excuse that putin gave before
attacking the donbass region and ukraine
at large
he inferred from this that time is
taking for india before it loses these
territories and that as the russia china
relationship has improved quite a lot
india shouldn't accept expect any help
from russia and instead turn towards the
west for alliances your view
we know
that china is currently way stronger
than india
that doesn't have to be i mean that's
not a matter of dispute at all
all you have to do is to look at the
size of the economies
india
india's economy is about one-fifth that
of china
china's economy is five times bigger
than india's economy and therefore they
have five times as much money that they
can invest in the military
for their military budget than india can
so there is a significant asymmetry at
play over here and yes we know that the
chinese
claim arunachal pradesh it happened
after mr vajpayee officially recognized
tibet as part of china
the consequence of that recognition was
that china immediately
made a claim to arunachal pradesh and
they are calling it south tibet we know
that
it's it's been known for quite some time
for two decades almost right
um
so the american person you're referring
to connected this with what put in with
the kind of claims that mr putin had
over the donbass region and parts of
ukraine
yeah it in a way it's similar but we
have to remember this
mr putin
ordered the invasion of a non-nuclear
armed nation
ukraine doesn't have nukes ukraine has a
massive army ukraine the ukrainian army
is
is larger than the
all the armies of western europe put
together
and yet mr putin has been able to
achieve i mean progressively achieve his
objectives and let's say there are more
objectives to be achieved most likely
so you cannot compare india with ukraine
the russia
ukraine dynamic is entirely different
from the china-india dynamic ukraine has
never been a great civilization a great
nation it's always been part of russia
historically no more rosia novorossiya
ukraine
the borderlands of russia new russia
that's what it is
and ukraine doesn't have a great
history of being a military force
military power and all that so the
russians had been planning this for i
would say a decade or so and this was
all executed properly the chinese may
also be planning in the future to
hopefully
maybe do an invasion
they must be hoping for for the
opportunity to arise for them to
possibly try an invasion of arunachal
that is always on the card yes
but india is not ukraine
india is a vastly different nation india
one very clear difference is that india
has nuclear weapons india has the
delivery systems india has multiple
modes of delivering nuclear weapons and
there are certain deadlines
that no indian government can afford to
let the chinese cross
you allow arunachal this to fall to
india you are doomed as you are doomed
politically you will never ever come to
power again no indian politician leader
or political party will ever allow such
a thing to happen
we know that the chinese have a better
more powerful military that military is
untested
yeah
and they are completely exposed in tibet
let's go to tibet let's take a look at
the
map where's the map here's the map
so we know where india is north of india
north of nepal we have tibet tibet is
is a is
there is no forest cover there
everything is clearly visible from the
sky
we have satellites india has satellites
in the sky observing
well various parts of the world that are
of interest to us let me i say
so yes we know what's happening in tibet
we know exactly where the chinese
military positions are in tibet where
their air bases are where their
infantry etc bases are
the indian positions
may not be so visible we may have
certain
well military
military bases etc air bases etc missile
bases missile launching places and so on
that are not visible because we have so
much forest cover in the eastern part of
india in the far east of india in assam
arunachal etc
so india has a massive advantage in this
region tactically speaking
and tibet is at a much higher higher
altitude than
the indian air bases which means that
the chinese aircraft aircraft fighter
planes etc if they were to to take off
from tibet they would be able to carry a
much
smaller
fuel load and weapons load than indian
aircraft that would
take off from much lower altitudes
right
so the chinese positions are completely
exposed in tibet
and india has an air advantage over the
chinese
so if if any hostilities were to break
out let's say the chinese go for
siliguri india could immediately just
respond by taking out all the chinese
military bases in this region
all the airports all the
army bases and whatnot we have missiles
that can
take out these bases with pinpoint
accuracy of course the chinese will also
launch missiles and all that would be
war
but india is in a very good position to
respond retaliate and
neutralize any chinese advance in this
region
so my point is this the americans
want india
to essentially become
a u.s for state
they want india to depend completely on
them
and
it's always good to to
show this big bogeyman which is actually
a real bogeyman
so india has no allies obviously russia
cannot help india if there's a war
between india and china as of today
russia is in no position to help india
because they also depend on china for a
number of things so if there is a
conflict between india and china the
russians will stay neutral they will
urge restraint they will urge a
ceasefire that is the best they can do
the russians are supplying india with
all kinds of
well
military equipment russia and china are
historically antagonistic towards each
other in the future
there will be conflict between russia
and china that is a given because they
share such a long common border and they
both eye each other's territory
especially the chinese are eyeing
russian territory that being said
india is not a pushover indian military
the indian military has been
will have been planning
this such scenarios for such scenarios
for a very long time all the war gaming
would be happening
about
about a
possible chinese incursion misadventure
into india and how to deal with it
various scenarios what do we do about it
that will be happening all the time
so india is very well prepared
and the americans can yeah well they
will do their best to persuade india to
to come into the american camp
but that is not
in india's long-term national interest
we will certainly cooperate with the u.s
in a variety of of of issues and matters
uh from on the economic front we will
cover we will extend full cooperation
and collaboration to the us on
geopolitical
matters on security matters we will give
issue based cooperation
based on each issue on a case by case
basis and so on that's how it's going to
be
we are obviously aware of the chinese
threat
the only nation
in asia that can counter the chinese
that the chinese sees a threat is india
so we are very well aware of it and we
would have taken all the precautions
necessary for that there is no way the
chinese
can capture arunachal pradesh or try
capturing it without suffering
catastrophic consequences
that is
a given
okay man of ashish says during the
second world war why did thailand allow
the japanese to move their troops
through their country to attack british
malaya
was it a political move and did thailand
face any kind of punishment from the
allies at the end after the end end of
the war
excellent question let's take a look at
the map as always to understand what we
are talking about
so
thailand obviously is our neighboring
country over here uh
our
island territories are just across the
andaman sea from thailand
and uh yeah so that's where thailand is
british malaya is over here
so in the second world war the japanese
had two options
they
there was one school of thought in the
japanese military that japan should take
over eurasia from the north
uh
they already had uh
conquered parts of manchuria they had
conquered they were on in the um
so they they occupied the manchoku
region what they called manchester which
is now present in china
they
were thinking about going through land
take over mongolia take over central
asia and go westwards in in that way
take over parts of russia present in
russia the other school of thought was
japan should do island hopping and take
over
asia from the south
along the uh coastal regions of asia
so eventually it was decided to take
over asia from the south and the
japanese military launched on its
at once
during world war two and very rapidly
they took over much of china
uh the philippines
uh indonesia
and so on and so forth and then they
came up to thailand now thailand at the
time was an independent nation it was a
westernized nation there had been a
revolution kind of thing
uh
the king was in a precarious position
the chakri dynasty king rama the sixth i
think it was
and uh there was
a there were two or three power centers
in thailand at the time
and thailand had officially declared
itself as a neutral nation in this
entire conflict the world war ii right
now what happened is that the japanese
military proved to be completely
irresistible nobody could stop it it was
taking over country after country
it was an extraordinarily effective
fighting force they had a very strong
navy as well
and then they came to the doorstep of
thailand and and they wanted to do they
wanted to go further and take over malay
like you said british malaya and burma
and eventually they wanted to take over
india as well that was the objective of
the japanese
thailand said we are neutral we will not
allow you to to come in the ordination
you can go through other means
so in 1941 the japanese invaded thailand
it was a very brief invasion five hours
five days whatever it was
and the thais then said please stop stop
stop stop no for no more no more we will
allow you to transit through our nation
and the thai nation the thai government
entered into an alliance with japan why
did they do it because they had no
option
the two
uh
choices
that the thai government had
were choice a
japan invasion takes you over and then
they will see you as a hostile nation
and they may do all kinds of atrocities
like they were doing elsewhere choice b
allow the japanese to use your territory
as a transiting
region
and to do that you have to enter into an
alliance with japan so the better option
for them
was to enter into an official alliance
with japan and allow them to go through
thailand so that's what happened so as a
result of that there was no
occupation of thailand by japan the
japanese military was definitely there
they used thailand as a waypoint is a
transit transiting region
but
the thai government was allowed to stay
in place
and uh yeah so thailand
was uh
able to save itself from a complete
disaster by doing this
obviously eventually the japanese lost
they where did they lose where did they
start losing
they they actually invaded india
they invaded eastern india they took
over myanmar burma etc they took over
the andaman nicobar islands yeah
and then they invaded the eastern part
of india the far east of india which is
present in nagaland and manipur
so there was the battle of kohima
and the battle of hinfal on the
outskirts of the city of impal this was
a long siege actually it was not
something that happened in over one day
this was a long long long process and in
the japanese were finally beaten back
from imphal and kohima along with the
japanese we have the indian national
army the ina of sebastian rabos and so
on so the japanese were beaten back from
there and that's where they started
losing and they kept on losing that's
what happened
eventually the japanese were beaten back
and we know what happened in hiroshima
and nagasaki thailand was liberated well
they found themselves free of the
japanese
and they had officially allied
with japan so did they face any
consequences any punishment from the
allies not really
they found themselves to be again very
lucky
i think the allies the americans and the
british they uh understood
that the thai government had actually
they had no choice
they faced complete disaster complete
destruction
or they could compromise and allow the
japanese to use thailand as a transiting
region
so in essence thailand
allowed agreed to become a vasa state of
japan they officially were the
government was officially still in power
but the japanese could do whatever they
wanted if they so wished
so the thai government had no choice
it was well under complete duress
and that's probably why the allies did
not punish thailand in any way
so that is the story in brief
okay arhan khan says my grandfather is a
pashtun he is very fair-skinned he has
blue eyes i haven't seen an indian
person with blue eyes so what can be the
reason behind that all right
so your grandfather is a pashtun and he
has blue eyes now do we have indians who
have blue eyes i think there are lots of
indians with blue eyes if you
travel
to certain parts of india
in kashmir we we know that there are
lots of people who have blue eyes right
in western india
in rajasthan gujarat even parts of
maharashtra etc you have people who have
eyes that are not
your typical brown indian eyes look at
my eyes i have brown eyes this i believe
is the standard eye color in india among
the among most indians
in parts of western india rajasthan
gujarat even parts of maharashtra we
have people who have got green eyes blue
eyes
um
hazel eyes or whatever
in rajasthan gujarat
in other parts of india also i suppose
you will find people who have blonde
hair red hair
especially in childhood so typically a
person who has blonde hair and childhood
as they grow older their hair gets
darker that's typically what you see
hair color changes
i can you can think of many examples
from sport indians follow cricket think
of brittley think of uh
what's that other guy
think of bradley think of sean pollock
these guys sean pollock had red hair
when he when he first came into the
scene today he's got dark hair brittley
had blonde hair today he's got dark hair
as well
and so on there are lots of other
examples shane watson and so on so
typically a person who is who is born
with blonde hair as they grow older the
hair becomes darker
but in western india and gujarat is fun
other places you will find people
especially children who have blonde hair
or blondish hair and reddish hair and
eyes that are green or or red or
whatever or sorry blue or whatever so
let me give you one example that came in
the news
let me uh
bring let me share my screen
this was a person
who uh
who lives
in the west
it's a lady
let me show you this
for some reason this this made it to the
news it's a lady called puja ganatra i
think she's of gujarati origin
and
apparently she demanded a dna test
because she was shunned by some people
am i really indian or whatever so as you
can see this lady
has red hair and if you look at her eyes
i think her eyes are blue right
let's look at the close-up she's got
blue eyes red hair
uh yeah this is how she looked as a kid
she's indian
as you can see
these are her parents
they're indian and she looks rather
rather european but obviously she is of
indian origin so that's just one example
there are lots of other people
it is obviously
quite rare in india to find people who
have got blonde hair or red hair
or blue eyes but it is there
and i think it is a little more
prevalent in in gandhar in afghanistan
i think many pashtuns have got blue eyes
some of them even have red hair
so that's how it is
what are the genetic causes behind this
we it is still to be seen there is very
little
genetic information or research that has
been done thus far in india we know that
the pashtuns are an extension of the
north indian population
not the turkmens or the turks or the
uzbeks or whatever but
the pashtuns the pashtuns are an
extension of the indian population or
the of the or overall indian population
persons some persons claim they're
they're of jewish origin or whatever
those are myths my friends you are not
jews you are him jews at most at best
so that's what it is it is there
fair skin red hair blonde hair blue eyes
you find these
characteristics among some indians it's
a rare trait but it is still there
okay naman says i was going through an
article about johannes having similar
public cultural similar similarities
with the hungarian paganism and their
culture
they drew similarities between the
johannes johanns of chakambari and the
white hans their kola devi etc
is there any real possible connection
between the two or is it near
speculation see we know there were there
were hernik invasions in india
during the uh time period of the gupta
empire about 1500 or so years roughly
before today the hernik invasions
happened in india in waves wave after
wave after wave of herniate invasions at
the same time as the horns were invading
rome as well
the homes were a
nomadic people
who lived in across eurasia where is
eurasia let me show you the map
here is the map
so this entire region north of china the
kazakhstan mongolia and southern russia
region all of this is the central asian
step the european step
and the hunnic peoples have essentially
the same origin as the mongolian people
right
so there were nomadic people
a polytheistic culture it is now called
tangerism or whatever
and they tried invading india for a very
long time
way afterward of invasion
eventually after the decline of the
gupta empire
the hoans succeeded
in various hudnik principalities were
set up into in india and
there they had a couple of kings who
were very evil someone like uh mihir kul
who was an atheist and he oppressed
everybody in western india in the
afghanistan pakistan region
he uh the the buddhists were deeply
unhappy with me so were the brahmins and
so on
so miracle was evil he was a very
oppressive cruel unjust ruler but later
honig kings
very rapidly
became part of the indian population
they uh
they took up indian culture they became
great uh
proponents of dharma
or some of them were
they patronized indian
arts cultures
sciences and so on
and the hons they established a kingdom
in afghanistan i believe it was
king
who built the
great statues of the buddha in bamiyan
region and so on they defended india for
quite some time against the islamic
turkic invasions eventually we know what
happened
now the question is
are the rajputs the chauhan's do they
have anything anything to do with the
horns do they have a hernic origin
not quite
there could be a little bit of hunic uh
you know ancestry possibly half a
percent one percent somewhere in most
people
in western india northern india because
the homes did
assimilate into the indian population no
doubt about that
their homes
conquered certain parts of india they
established some kingdoms and eventually
they assimilated among the indian
population just the way the greeks did
same way
so people in north india western india
etc afghanistan pakistan and so on
many of them would have a little bit of
fractional hunik ancestry
but the great
lineages such as the chauhan's the
hamanas etc the various rajput lineages
they date back to the vedic era
so who are the rajputs essentially the
rajputs are the old aristocracy the old
ruling lineages the ruling clans
and how many of these clans were there
maybe 36 or maybe more or something so
these all originate in ancient india
there could be a little bit of blood
here and there it doesn't mean that the
origin is honnik
or if or if from the skittions or
whatever skittions also the indus
keithians they invaded india about 2000
or so india years ago they also
established kingdoms massive kingdoms in
western india they also were great
proponents of dharma
and yeah i mean this ketians themselves
had indian origin
so india is a big
receptacle of various such nomadic
races but the overall contribution to
the indian gene pool was minimal
nomads are very small in number they
occupy a vast they ruled vast regions of
eurasia but they were very small in
numbers yeah so they could not really
contribute much to the indian gene pool
barring a few drops you know so um
there are similarities culturally
between the huns between the people of
the balkan regions and so on with india
there could be ancient ties but those
relations that you see this cultural
similarities originate in india let me
give you an interesting example of that
let's take a look at balkan culture
shall we
um let me show you
let me once again share my screen go to
google and take a look at albanian
culture for instance albania is a small
nation in the western in the balkans
albanian
culture
albanian dresses etc if you look at
traditional albanian dresses etc
you will see some turkic some turkish
style in that
you can see some some turkish influence
but overall
it seems in some ways quite similar to
the dressing style and the culture
of people in western india rajasthan
gujarat etc
in some ways it's quite similar to that
especially the way the men
uh dress you know
check it out
so there are similarities now how do
this what is the origin of these
similarities and all that we don't quite
know nobody has bothered to
research this in any great detail
but it's there we can see that there is
some connection there we don't know what
the connection is
so there are connections and all that
but it doesn't mean that all of this
came from abroad
india is the oldest civilization if
there is any
transmission of culture it is outwards
from india
so uh there is no evidence whatsoever
that the hamanas
etc have a foreign origin or any other
rajput clan all the rajput plants are
of indian
origin
okay renegade the fox says it is said in
the puyas in the that the imphal valley
was under water centuries back many
centuries back in the first dry land is
known to be the kangla during excavation
pottery that is over as old as 17 to 21
000 years old carbon dating was found in
the kangla region
does it mean that the first early
settlement in kangla was 20 thousand
years old is there any archaeological
evidence that the conglomerate might
have in the first dry place in the
infant valley and how long ago would
that have dried out okay so we are
talking about manipur do you all know
where manipur is i suppose people would
not know let's so let's take a look at
the map first
in order to geolocate the region that we
are talking about
which part of india we're talking about
manipur is in the far east of india
which other people call northeast india
here is manipur this is manipur the city
of imphal and that's where you have the
kangala the kangla is an ancient fort
that is at least 2 000 years old and
apparently there's a portrait of this
far that's found there that's about 17
21 000 years old so let's take a look at
where the kangla is
so according to the puyas the puyas are
the old literature of of the manipuri
people
so according to the puyas
uh
the kangla
was the first dry region the first dry
land in the entire world
uh so if you see the imphal region it's
a valley
the imphal region is it's called the
imphal valley it is surrounded by hills
by i believe seven rings of hills you
can't quite see it very clearly here you
would need google earth or something to
understand that very well but as you can
see it's it's a flat piece of land flat
region of land there is a big lake here
the loktak lake very great place for
tourism
and around this valley you have seven
rings of hills
so it's a very inaccessible region it's
very hard to reach there unless you go
by plane obviously which makes it very
easy
and
according to manipura tradition
the kangla
was the first place over here that was
that had dry land so it is possible that
in the past this entire valley was
submerged it was flooded we see some
evidence of that in the lake which is
the deepest the the lowest point in this
region
so maybe uh 2000 years ago this entire
valley may have been flooded it is
possible
uh
thus far sufficient research has not
been done about that so we don't know
but if the oral tradition or the written
tradition of in the puja says that it
could be true so
you could do some analysis of the region
to find out now
the kangla region the kangla fort is in
the heart of imphal city
yeah over here
there's a gate and there's a moat around
it and
there is this
temple the pakhangba temple and there is
the ancient royal palace which is no
longer there it is an archaeological
site
this region over here is an ancient
archaeological site and there could be
much more if you go there you will see
that there is so much
that is underground and needs to and uh
remains to be discovered
so it is quite possible that uh see
according to the royal chronicle of
manipur the caitanya
uh
the
ningtawja dynasty may have started
around 36 a.d
that is one version the other version
says it is like 3500 years old so uh
even that is not quite well known yet
because nobody is doing any research the
i wonder what the great historians in
the manipur university are doing what
are they doing
why aren't they why aren't they
researching this anyway
so
uh according to what's said here
some pottery has been discovered there
that is 17 to 21 000 years old that is
astonishing if it is true
so i haven't found
from my very cursory research thus far
or any evidence of this claim
that pottery has been found that is 17
17 or 21 000 years old i don't think
there's any portrait anywhere in the
world from my knowledge that is that old
so i will have to look into this further
but just to show all of you where the
kangla fort is
and uh yeah
uh so i would be skeptical about this
claim
that there is pottery that's 17 to 21
000 years old that would revolutionize
world history actually
so i will do some further research to
try and find the source of this claim
but uh
about your other questions
uh it is quite likely it is quite
possible that maybe kangla the kangla
fort region was the first part of the
infall valley that became dry and
eventually the whole valley because of
climate change or whatever dried out
apart from the loktak lake it is
possible
so it's a very interesting part of india
and a great place for tourism
okay luncheon buses what's your opinion
on iran and azerbaijan trying to claim
that polo originated in their land
persia
and trying to declare it as their
national sport
they said that the mughals caught both
brought polo to india it was taken by
the british from india
and he died playing polo okay listen
they can claim whatever they want some
people claim that even chess originated
from persia we know that chess
originated in india there is undeniable
evidence
from the
from western india the port of lothal
in gujarat which is now an
archaeological site they decide they
discovered a chess
board made out of rock over there
yeah with chess pieces
that dates back about four five thousand
years before today so it's undeniable
that chess originated in india and
nobody is now able to dispute the claim
now some people are trying to claim that
iran or azerbaijan is the birthplace
birthplace of polo once again that's a
lie
polo again originated in manipur okay
manipur is the birthplace of polo the
british discovered polo in manipur the
world's oldest polo ground is in info
let me once again show you them show you
the map
show you the map there is info this is
involved right we were in infall where
is the polo ground
it's somewhere in the center of imphal
somewhere in the central region of
imphal
maybe it's here
yes this is the world's oldest polo
ground it is around
at least 2 000
years
old right
so the british discovered polo in
manipur
they started playing it maybe the
iranians were playing some game that is
similar to that but it is not as old as
the one that was played in manipur now
let me show you what this polo ground
actually looks like the world's oldest
polo ground
just give me a second
okay let me share that
all right let's share the screen and
let's take a look at the imphal polo
ground which is the world's oldest polo
ground this is what it looks like it is
still in use
this this polo ground is still in use we
gave the world the game of polo
they play tournaments there all the time
international tournaments
in imphal city in um
in the world's oldest polo ground so let
us let it be very clear
that
manipur is the birthplace of polo not
iran not azerbaijan not not whatever
else they can keep claiming it but that
makes no difference it's like trying to
claim that sumo wrestling originated in
iran
that sort of thing you know
uh
various people try to appropriate other
other cultures
discoveries and inventions cultural
appropriation they are trying to claim
that greece was the origin of indian
mathematics you know that sort of thing
the the turks are trying to claim that
feta cheese is turkish it's not it's
greek
and so on
so let's be clear the origin of polo i
don't know about kathmandu
whatever
it's manipur nowhere
else swapnil says
what do you think about the three
country proposal with respect to the
israel-palestine conflict in which gaza
can merge with egypt and the west bank
can merge with jordan
as these territories share historic
cultural ties with those countries and
the rest of israel remains under israeli
rule okay so
there are three proposals let me show
you once again what these proposed what
what's what this region looks like
instead of going to the map let me show
you an image
of a map of this region that is color
coded
for better understanding
so this is the region
all right though what is the west bank
let me show you the bigger perspective
first then i will show you this image so
that you know you get a better idea
let's go to the to the actual map first
let's uh move out of info
and go
westwards all right zooming out zooming
out let's go to the mediterranean region
and this here is the region that we are
talking about
israel jordan egypt syria and so on
so this is israel and if you zoom in
over here this is the west bank
why do they call it the west bank it is
the west bank of the river jordan you
will find a river here the jordan river
all right
so the west bank region
is the western bank is on the western
bank of the jordan river
now there are three now let me show you
and and to the south you have egypt as i
hope you know
to the west of israel to the east of
israel jordan to the north east you have
syria
to the absolute north of lebanon and to
the e to the west and south you have
egypt
now let me show you that image again
for better understanding because it is
color coded
so there are three proposals
there is a one nation proposal which
says that
israel
should merge with gaza in the west bank
there should be only one state one
nation
and also the golan region possibly
and that should be the only solution
just one nation
there is a two-state proposal which says
that
the west bank region
should become independent an independent
palestinian state
and the other state should be israel
the third proposal is a three-nation
proposal which says
that gaza should merge with egypt
the west bank should merge with jordan
and israel israel remains independent
these are the three different proposals
one state proposal two state proposal
and three state proposal
now
so that that's what it actually is
these are the three solutions or
proposals now
which which of these is most likely the
question is
why would israel
give up so much territory what does it
gain
in exchange yes it will gain some peace
for some time in exchange but remember
just just like india and pakistan if
someone like manmohan singh were to give
away kashmir to pakistan do you think
the india pakistan conflict would end no
it will not end
the pakistanis the the the
root cause of the conflict is not
kashmir kashmir is an excuse you give it
away to pakistan the pakistanis will
still be antagonistic to india they will
still try and indulge in terrorism with
india their actual objective is to
conquer the whole of india and destroy
it
that is the real objective similarly
if israel were to accept the let's say
two-state proposal that palestine the
the west bank and gaza becoming become
independent
and they become a palestinian state
the palestinians will still
fight the israelis it will solve nothing
you see
and the three-state proposal is that
west the west bank merges with
with jordan like you see here
and uh
gaza becomes part of egypt
well i don't think the jordanian
jordanians want the west bank to become
part of jordan sure they they will gain
some territory but they are ethnically
and culturally different from the people
of the west bank the so-called
palestinians
there is significant opposition
within jordan
to
the west bank becoming part of jordan
because then the palestinians will be
free to move within jordan and they
could overwhelm the local population
there is already a significant
palestinian population in jordan and
they don't want the palestinians to
become a majority in their nation which
would mean political loss of power and
much much more
it could lead to cultural erosion and
take over what and all that so there is
a significant amount of opposition and
resistance from within jordan
politically and etc against the west
bank becoming part of jordan
it's a very complex situation
it's all been created by the western
powers
so so that's where we are
so as of today there is no solution
the west bank is still a
de facto governed by by israel the
israelis
there are israeli regions also
settlements within the west bank and
there is constant conflict
with the west bank with gaza and so on
so that's where we are there is no
solution right now right now there are
three different solutions that have been
proposed but none of them
seems to be acceptable to everybody
least to all israel so right now we
don't know what the solution is we are
at a stalemate
okay next the question
okay uh i don't know what the name is it
says when you were collaborating with
the jaipur dialogues regarding the
joyshankar doctrine and ajit duwal
doctrine you said that if india becomes
nearly as powerful as china then its
relations with china may improve but in
the previous video you also said that no
superpowers no two superpowers can or
will share a long border am i missing
something could you please elaborate on
this all right good question now first
of all let me address the question of
the jaishankar doctrine and the
so-called ajit dual doctrine the
jaishankar doctrine is something i have
spoken about maybe i gave the name
jaishankar doctrine i have never spoken
about any ajit dual doctrine if it
exists we don't know what it is
okay and there is this uh well
there is this uh perception that's been
created there is a conflict apparently
between mr doval and mr jaishankar there
is absolutely no evidence to that that
claim is completely baseless right if
there is actually a doctrine it's a modi
doctrine
and
the manifestation of the modi doctrine
in the
external affairs sphere is what we can
call the jejunga doctrine
and if there is a dual doctrine that
also is a manifestation of the overall
modi doctrine but from the uh
internal security etc
perspective
right
so
any any claim that there is a conflict
between mr joshua and mr doctor mr duval
is baseless what is the evidence for
that
it's it's so so i completely disagree
with that let me put that on on the
record
uh both mr jayshankar and mr dual serve
at the pleasure of the prime minister of
india
and their only objective and their only
job their only duty is to carry out
the policies that the prime minister has
formulated
so whatever they are doing is in
synchronicity with each other and with
the prime minister's overall large-scale
vision for the country
so let me just place that on the record
now
i said there on the jaipur dialogues
if i okay
that if india becomes nearly as powerful
as china then relations may improve but
i also said that no two superpowers can
share a long common border
there is nothing
wrong with either of the statements
india is not a superpower
china is not a superpower if india
becomes nearly as powerful as china
there will be both great regional powers
there will not be superpowers
right now there is only one superpower
the united states the chinese aim to
displace and replace the us as the only
superpower right now they are no match
to the us they cannot afford to have a
hot war for the u.s they will be
destroyed completely
the chinese are in no position to fight
the us
militarily or even economically right
now
so if india rises
to a position that's comparable with
china there could be a period
of cooperation between india and china
it will not be forever cooperation
if the us declines and india and china
become the two great powers in the world
there is going to be conflict between
india and china i'm talking about a
small period maybe a few years of
cooperation india and china are always
going to be rivals as long as there is a
common border unless tibet becomes free
again india and china will
definitely enter into a conflict in the
future
so that's the point look at the big
picture i said something don't look at
it that statement in isolation look at
it from the bigger perspective
india and china may cooperate for some
time
because
if india becomes more powerful the
chinese will not find it
in their favor to fight india because
the more powerful india can destroy
china even today the chinese can't fight
india because india has the ultimate
weapon that they fear
so that's what i mean
the chinese are not a superpower india
is not a superpower there's only one
superpower as long as there's a bigger
threat to the chinese they may for some
time wish to cooperate with the
more powerful india but eventually india
and china will be in conflict unless
tibet again becomes free in which case
there could be peace between india and
china even if both become superpowers
so that is the nuanced and large
big picture answer to your question
okay siddharth says you mentioned about
angus medicine's gdp analysis how india
was the richest nation for close to the
2000 or plus years
sorbet but did chingus khan and other
invaders know about this about mr
madison's analysis or the fact that
india was rich because this analysis of
gdp is recent
and maybe the ancient world didn't know
that india was the richest and maybe
that's why
didn't invade india
see
when you are
when you are rich
everyone knows
you can't hide
the fact that you are the greatest
economy in the world
let's say you are a rich person
you live in a certain neighborhood
eventually everybody will know that you
are rich people have
a very inquisitive nature people want to
look into their neighbors affairs what
is this what is this person up to what
is that family up to
if you are rich everybody will know you
simply can't help it even if you try to
live the most meager lifestyle
now india
is not a small nation it's not a small
geographical region you see india is the
figure on the map it's an enormous
geographical region it's a subcontinent
sized geographical territory
india has been trading india had been
trading with the entire world for
thousands of years
everyone knew how rich india was
india had been trading with rome
india was trading with egypt india was
trading with the greeks india was
trading massively massively with the
chinese india was trading with southeast
asia for thousands of years
everyone knew about india
you can't hide
an enormous civilization like india and
the scale of wealth that it possessed
so
yeah we know there was no gdp analysis
at the time angus medicine didn't exist
then
but india's
reputation preceded itself it wherever
it went even in rome people were aware
of how incredibly wealthy india was
everywhere people knew it
so it's not like india was some obscure
nation in some
half forgotten corner of the world look
at the map india occupies a central
position in the world everybody knew
about india
why did vasco da gama want to come to
india what was columbus looking for why
did he want to come to india why did the
europeans why were the europeans so
desperate to come to india
because they knew how incredibly
fabulously wealthy india was and they
wanted a piece of that everybody knew
how well the india was india was the
wealthiest of all
is is it possible chinese khan didn't
know about it
india's wealth dwarfed that of the quran
empire which he destroyed
for good reason
i mean it was a just war so
it's
un inconceivable
that a great conqueror like chingish
khan would not have known
how incredibly fabulously wealthy india
was it is inconceivable it's simply
impossible nobody
though there could be no great power or
ruler in the world or king in the world
who would not know how well the india
was
all right i hope that explains this
laksha says if the events that are
described described in the ramayana
happened over twelve thousand years ago
why did bhagwan sridham have to
construct the rama sayto wasn't the
island of lanka connected to bharat by
land at the time
12 000 years ago there was we were still
in the middle of the ice age the last
the last ice age and yes
the water levels the sea levels
across the world were much lower than
what they are today the indian landmass
was much larger and sri lanka was
connected it was very much part of the
indian sub continent there was no
uh
body of water between natural and cut it
was all connected right yeah we know
that
no doubt
so the assumption that is made in this
question
is that the ramayan happened more than
12 000 years ago how do you know that
how do we know that the ramayana
happened more than 12 000 years ago
has anybody successfully conclusively
authoritatively
dated the ramayana there are many claims
lots of people have come up with a whole
lot of different different claims none
of those claims has been proven thus far
one person making a claim is not proven
if a person makes a claim it has to be
proven by other people that yes we have
verified the claims that this person has
made we have verified all the
calculations and this person is correct
and multiple sources have to corroborate
this only then can you say that a claim
has been proven if a person goes all
around the place saying that it's this
much this many years old it's just a
claim that person may possibly be right
but has anybody verified it many people
are saying that other claims are valid
so let us not jump the gun let's not get
ahead of you ourselves
no claim has been proven thus far all
claims thus far i would say are equally
valid
only when you have a proper
detailed long-term large-scale
uh
verification of all the claims that is
done only then will we be able to know
exactly based on archaeology astronomy
when did the events of the ramayana
happen
and why are there so many different
claims with both so many wildly
disparate dates because all of these
researchers are interpreting the
sanskrit verses differently
and they are maybe doing the
calculations also differently
so right now none of these claims has
been proven so let's not
start believing any of the claims
i'm not trying to
demean or disparage any of these
researchers these people have spent
years of their lives
are doing all the calculations and
putting forth whatever the date they
found we must appreciate their hard work
their effort their dedication to the
cause of indian culture and civilization
and history
we must appreciate that
but right now none of the claims has
been proven
okay so yes twelve thousand years ago
srilanka was part of india
but we know
that a build a bridge was built
and that kind of
you know what that does
that raises significant questions about
that claim of twelve thousand plus years
ago
and i believe some people are saying
that the sri lanka that we have today is
not the original sri lanka the original
training was in the maldives how
ridiculous is that how incredibly
ridiculous is that there is only one
lanka
which is today's sri lanka there is no
other lanka that sort of work around to
justify your claim is nonsense
so yeah that's what i have to say there
is zero evidence
that the events of the ramayana happened
more than 12 000 years ago there are
claims people have claimed various
things
none of these claims have been proven so
we will have to be patient we still
don't know when the ramayana happened
okay let us take a couple of questions
more
where is it
one second all right
kus
all right says that i recently came
across a video of a food vlogger in
guyana
he was eating guyanese puri in dal
this not only sounds like our own puri
and dal it looked like it too
this had me wondering about a country in
south america having indian influence
can you please tell us the history
behind this all right
where's the map
we have to look at this wonderful
country called guyana where is it where
is it where is it
where is it
let me pull up the map and let's go to
guyana
google maps
all right where is guyana
so you know where india is
you know where india is let's orient
ourselves let's go westwards westwards
westwards atlantic ocean westwards and
we are here at the americas now let's go
slightly southwards
and here is the nation
the present-day nation of guyana
yeah this is a highly tropical base
very warm very humid
so this is the nation you're talking
about
it was called british guyana earlier
and there is a french guyana here also
there is this place called kuhu from
where they launch rockets aryan rockets
but we are talking about guyana
georgetown is the cap is the capital
city of ghana
so why
did you discover something indian there
so now that you know where vienna is let
me show you something else
uh
guyana
the nation of guyana contributes qriket
players to the west indies cricket team
all right
so the west indies cricket team
has players
from guyana let's take a look at some of
these players here one second
let's take a look at some of the
guyanese cricket players let me share
the screen with you
guyanese qriket players
check out these people
taganara and chandrapal gudakesh bhuti
veerasami parmol
chandrapol hemraj
you can see so many vishal singh
and
list of international cricketers from
guyana let's see some more
rohan kanhai indian alvin kalichan
another indian shivnara and chandra paul
rand
and so on so forth so as you can see
lots of guyanese cricketers
have indian origin and
overall the nation of guyana
uh if you look at the religious
demographics in guyana i think at least
25 percent or around 25 percent
of the population of guyana practices
hinduism
why is it so
so clearly more than 25 percent more
than a quarter of the guyanese
population is of indian origin because
many of them have converted to
christianity
so how did this happen so so what you
have seen is obviously indian culture
it's indian cuisine they still eat
indian food there so what happened let
me show you what happened and how did
this end end up being the way it is
let me
show you what happened
i've shared this image before i'm
sharing it again
so
between the 19th century between 1835
and 1917
the british
forced
about a million indians
to travel to other parts they
essentially shipped off
about a million indians officially to
various parts of the world to work as
indentured laborers indentured laborers
means you will essentially work as a
slave but you'll be given a certain
amount of money
and you have to work for a certain
number of years and you are not allowed
to go back to india so this was
permanent deportation from india
about half a million
to uh
parts of africa 150 000 to south africa
tanzania etc and about 450 000 which is
almost half a million
to the west indies region
trinidad and to guyana
right so these indians were used as
essentially nothing more than slave
labor they were forced to work in sugar
in plantations other plantations work in
fields
and they were never allowed to go back
to india so that's where they settled
down and that's where their descendants
still live that's why you have so many
people of south african of indian origin
in south africa
because traditionally
for thousands of years indians have
lived traveled to africa lived there
traded there in eastern africa in kenya
etc but south africa there was very
little indian presence before the
indians were deported there by the
british similarly the caribbean region
you have so many indians who live there
guyana is in south america but yes even
guyana received lots of indians
so this entire caribbean region received
about half a million
indian so-called indentured laborers
and that's why you saw this food vlogger
showing
i mean eating guyanese puri and dal
and let me show you the kind of food
they eat in
south africa in durban etc
there is this famous dish called bani
chao that they eat over there which is
essentially nothing but bread
with some indian
stew
curry within this so this is like you
know
some indian food in inside bread so this
is a staple of the south african diet
even the non-indians eat it it's very
popular there
so you will see indian cuisine in all
these places where indians have been
forced to travel
to to in order to work as essentially
nothing more than slaves that is the
legacy of british of the british
occupation of
india
uh
kuldeep says as you said many times
and we learn this from history as well
all great thing things come to an end
because of poor succession my question
is simple who should be who or how
should be your successor see i spoke
about empires in kingdoms
empires rise because of great leadership
all empires eventually
crumble
because of poor leadership and poor
leadership happens because of poor
succession a great emperor may be
succeeded by a mediocre one
so when the succession grow goes wrong
that's when an empire
eventually declines and crumbles or a
kingdom
i am not an emperor
i am not a king i'm just a guy
so um you know who will be my successor
why don't you all be my successors you
know i mean i'm still
in
i'm i'm not about to abdicate my
position any anytime soon but yeah
what i'm doing is about spreading
knowledge whatever little i've learned
and i'm learning to all of you
and i'm very grateful and very very
honored that all of you watch this and
listen to me so i'm very grateful
you are all my successors
learn everything you wish to learn and
teach to others
so succession is typically about empires
about emperors and kings but
that's all i can say right
her says someday we might do a live
session in the metaverse
i don't know how we will control the
multiple questions then say some
something like arnab's debate i guess
yeah if the meta works takes off we
could do ask abhijit in the metaverse
and we could be all sitting in one big
room
in mid in the mid hours the metaverse
several thousand of us and maybe we
could have a q a session there i'm not
sure how we could moderate it like
you're saying
we would not want 15 people talking at
the same time but
yeah it could happen in the future let's
see if the meta hours become something
useful to all of us
okay
we are almost at the end let me take a
few questions from the live chat you
have questions for me ask me
in the live chat i will take some
questions
from the live chat
ask me some questions i haven't answered
before hopefully
um
what is my opinion on dr s jayshankar i
think he is the best foreign minister
external affairs minister we have had in
living memory
yeah
clearly aligned towards india's national
interest
and he is uh he's doing an
extraordinarily good job i think he's
the most impactful diplomat in world
geopolitics today great great i have the
highest of regard for dr s joshua
i've heard that jesus came to indian
kashmir is it true there is no evidence
0.0 evidence of that
can medieval
war force survive modern warfare if
reconstructed and maintained properly
all it takes is a cruise missile strike
to obliterate any kind of building no
matter how thick the walls
you have a war you have a missile with a
powerful enough warhead conventional
warhead it will take out any fort
whatsoever that's why medieval forts
don't exist i mean they're not used for
warfare anymore because it's pointless
absolutely pointless modern warfare has
gone way beyond that it's evolved far
beyond the medieval tactics so all
medieval tactics armor horseback
swords and spears and forts etc they
they are completely totally utterly
obsolete in today's world in the 21st
century
what's your opinion on katsa capsize the
u.s sanctions on on
because you acquired the military
technology
hardware etc from our nation that they
don't like that is katsa and obviously
we in india
have acquired
various russian
weapons systems including the s 400
weapon system so the americans were very
upset about this but now they have well
seen reason and they are on the verge of
giving
india an exemption to the sanctions
sanctions because well if they sanction
india it will backfire on them they need
india as a counterweight to china they
need india the india is
an integral part of of uh
of the quad they need india in that they
need to keep india well they
the last thing they want to do is to
sanction their own quad partner their
major quad partner the other nations in
the quad are japan and australia which
are both u.s colonies so essentially
it's us in india that's all it is and
it's a very important thing for them in
order to counter counter balance china
so obviously they were not going to
sanction india it's it's going to
backfire on them
if they do it so yeah uh it's almost a
done deal now that the uh
proposed sanctions are not going to
happen
well
where what was it i saw something and it
disappeared
um
do you like anime i as a kid i used to
really like cartoons japanese cartoons
and various other cartoons there was
something called robot tech i used to
watch a long time ago it's it's old
history so yeah but these days i no
longer have the time to watch stuff i no
longer watch anime or anything but yes
i used to like it a lot as a kid
great fun
anything else
future of nuclear energy i think nuclear
energy has a good future
it's a reasonably clean so for form of
energy as long as you don't let the
reactor melt down
and
modern reactors have lots of safeguards
checks and checks and balances that
ensure that the reactor will operate
safely
it's a very good form of energy it has
almost been zero carbon footprint the
germans are doing a ridiculous thing by
shutting down their nuclear reactors in
france
in france i think more than 70 of their
electricity comes from nuclear energy
how nice is that they don't need to burn
coal they don't need to burn gas they
don't need to burn any other fossil
fuels it's good
as long as you operate them properly
professionally nothing's gonna go wrong
uh you've had a couple of accidents
chernobyl
journalism is a good example is a bad
example terrible example
that was because of mistakes
fukushima well that was a tsunami like
you know like a once in a hundred years
kind of event so as long as you make
sure something like that doesn't happen
your reactions are safe
so i think nuclear energy is something
people
nations around the world should invest
in in the future hopefully we will be
able to tame
the fusion reaction which will be even
cleaner
than
the ordinary efficient reactors that we
have which do produce some some
nuclear waste fusion reactions will be
will be way cleaner than that i think
nuclear energy should be invested in and
it has a good future
okay with this we are at the end of
today's session
thank you all of you very much for all
the questions always great talking to
you all
next week we will do a session on
twitter again and a couple of other
sessions like this one
so until then take care thank you very
much and i will see you in the next
episode and we will keep on having these
wonderful interactions
thank you take care
bye